<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Milan Vukov</title>
    <link>https://mvukov.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mvukov.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Milan Vukov</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mvukov.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Milan Vukov</title>
      <link>https://mvukov.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>ACADO Toolkit</title>
      <link>https://mvukov.github.io/project/acado/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mvukov.github.io/project/acado/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ACADO Toolkit is a software environment and algorithm collection for automatic control and dynamic optimization. It provides a general framework for using a great variety of algorithms for direct optimal control, including model predictive control, state and parameter estimation and robust optimization. ACADO Toolkit is implemented as a self-contained C++ code and user-friendly API. The object-oriented design allows for convenient coupling of existing optimization packages and for extending it with user-written optimization routines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my PhD days, the developments of ACADO used to be mostly focused around the auto-generated optimization solvers with the idea to employ those on fast mechatronics systems. I have spent quite a bit of my time on the solvers for nonlinear MPC and MHE. Compared to the starting point of my developments, at the end of my PhD we achieved the state of far more capable package and an order of magnitude faster generated code. Besides algorithmic implementations, I contributed to the code base maintenance: we started using CMake as a build system, we moved code repository to Git and we set up a continuous integration system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More about the code-generation tool (CGT) can be found e.g. in Chapter 4 of my &lt;a href=&#34;ftp://ftp.esat.kuleuven.be/pub/SISTA/mvukov/reports/thesis_final_print.pdf&#34;&gt;PhD thesis&lt;/a&gt;. For other publications on the topic please refer to my &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=gnSTyOMAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;oi=ao&#34;&gt;Google Scholar&lt;/a&gt; profile. Despite being a PhD-grade software package (read: no (unit-)tests, developed mainly for an increase of personal publication counters), the tool has been successfully used in a number of academic applications even without any help from the development team. Furthermore, we have learned through various channels that the generated code has been used in some commercial applications. That is brave and certainly contributes to the success of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MPC and MHE for a laboratory scale overhead crane</title>
      <link>https://mvukov.github.io/project/crane_experiments/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mvukov.github.io/project/crane_experiments/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YuiSrqe7rlo&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first application of an auto-generated Nonlinear Model Predictive Control (MPC) from the ACADO toolkit. The experiments are explained in detail in &lt;a href=&#34;http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=6315390&#34;&gt;this publication&lt;/a&gt;. Although the tracking was slow, we showed that we can run the so-called &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;eal-&lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;ime &lt;strong&gt;i&lt;/strong&gt;teration (RTI) scheme in hard real-time. Furthermore, experiments proved a fast convergence rate of the RTI scheme. This implementation used a simple MPC formulation and a simple estimator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the improved experiments are published in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifac-papersonline.net/Detailed/68307.html&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;. We used a more detailed model and a more complex formulation for the MPC. Moreover, this time we used nonlinear Moving Horizon Estimation (MHE) to more accurately estimate the system&#39; states. As a result, faster motions are achieved. Below is the video of the improved experiments. Besides faster motions, we also achieved faster execution times of the controller and the estimator: we used a newer version of the code generator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QEf05rTS-BE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A detailed comparison of the two aforementioned approaches can be found in Chapter 5 of my &lt;a href=&#34;ftp://ftp.esat.kuleuven.be/pub/SISTA/mvukov/reports/thesis_final_print.pdf&#34;&gt;PhD thesis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rotational Start-up of an Airborne Wind Energy System</title>
      <link>https://mvukov.github.io/project/awe_experiments/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mvukov.github.io/project/awe_experiments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alright, what is Airborne Wind Energy (AWE) about?&lt;/em&gt; Good one, you can find more about it &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Airborne_wind_turbine&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or just watch the video below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1UmN3MiR65E&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what were we doing at KU Leuven? Among many amazing things, we have used to spend huge amounts of time modeling, simulating, optimizing and controlling AWE systems. Before energy production, one needs to launch the kite in the sky. One way to do it is to utilize the concept of the rotational start-up. We have made a small scale setup at our lab and we used that setup for testing and demonstration purposes. In particular, to play with fast algorithms and solvers for nonlinear Model Predictive Control (MPC) and moving horizon estimation (MHE).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qta9N8gNRyk&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above you can see then work-in-progress video (Q4 2014) of a first-person view on the Leuven kite carousel experiments. Here we demonstrated the closed-loop performance with MPC and MHE. The goal of the experiments was to achieve stable movements from one steady-state to the other one, which are characterized mostly by the roll angle and the height of the plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The screen on the left serves for the live feed of the data coming from sensors and the data the controllers send to the actuators:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;top row: gyroscope, accelerometer and winch data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bottom row: control surfaces (ailerons and the elevator control surfaces&#39; deflection angles),
main motor speed and control, and the line angle sensor data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the MHE horizons on the screen on right. The current pose estimate is the one that is not shaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system was modeled with an index-3 DAE (27 differential states, 4 inputs, and 1 algebraic state). Both MHE and the MPC work at a 25 Hz rate in a unified control-estimation cycle. Horizon for the MHE was set to be 30 intervals (1.2 seconds). For the controller, we chose 50 intervals (2 seconds).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, about 4 years of team-work in the lab have been summarized in Chapter 6 of my &lt;a href=&#34;ftp://ftp.esat.kuleuven.be/pub/SISTA/mvukov/reports/thesis_final_print.pdf&#34;&gt;PhD thesis&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0967066115300095&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;. The chapter has quite more details on the hardware setup, while the paper has more information regarding the results (the paper has been revised, corrected and published after the defense). Unfortunately, since my funding was running out and the team was considerably decimated, there is no comparison of the performance of different controllers and estimators in the paper. That is the main reason why the paper has been written as (a yet another) application of MPC &amp;amp; MHE using the ACADO code-generation tool&#39; features, then indeed to a challenging system. To my knowledge, in 2015 (and possibly quite a bit afterward) that paper reported the most challenging use-case of nonlinear MPC and MHE on a mechatronics system given the model dimensions and horizons of the controller and the estimator. Besides showing off real-world experiments and real-time capability of the implementation, we have also honestly reported certain unsatisfactory results and discussed the limitations of the approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;links-to-some-software-used-for-experiments&#34;&gt;Links to some software used for experiments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acadotoolkit.org&#34;&gt;ACADO toolkit&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; code generation for nonlinear MPC and MHE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.casadi.org&#34;&gt;CasADi&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; nonlinear optimization, code generation for symbolics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/giaf/hpmpc&#34;&gt;HPMPC&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; QP solver for linear MPC and MHE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orocos.org&#34;&gt;OROCOS&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; real-time middleware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pyqtgraph.org/&#34;&gt;PyQtGraph&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; real-time capable line plotter in Python (yes, in Python)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.qpoases.org&#34;&gt;qpOASES&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; QP solver&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ghorn/rawesome&#34;&gt;rawesome&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; modeling environment for AWE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
